A Guide to the Charles P. Cardwell Jr. Collection
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Charles P. Cardwell, Jr. Collection 1950-1953
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
91/Aug/15
.6 linear ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Dr. Lauren Woods, Vice President of Health Sciences, Virginia Commonwealth University.
Biographical/Historical Information
Charles P. Cardwell Jr. was born 5 June, 1903 in Hanover County, Virginia. He attended Randolph-Macon College and Virginia Polytechnic Institute where he excelled in Engineering. By 1935 he was a licensed civil engineer in Kentucky. He became director of the buildings and grounds department at the Medical College of Virginia in 1940. In 1945 he also served as assistant director of the hospital division.
Cardwell became director of the hospital division in 1947. For the next 22 years he served as director of the teaching hospitals until his retirement in 1969. He was awarded MCV's first honorary doctorate (hospital administration) in 1962, and established the curriculum for the school of health administration. He served as president of the Virginia Hospital Association, Virginia Blue Cross, and the Richmond Hospital Council in addition to memberships in many other local civic organizations.
Cardwell received the American Hospital Association's Distinguished Service Award in 1970. Cardwell was granted emeritus professor status after his retirement in 1969. He was also awarded the Virginia Commonwealth University Medical School's first distinguished service to medicine award in 1975.
After his retirement Cardwell was active in the MCV alumni society, he served on several administrative councils, and still found time to teach a class once a week. Cardwell died 19 July, 1977 at the age of 74.
Scope and Content
This Collection contains the personal papers of Charles P. Cardwell, Jr. when he served as president-elect, then president of the Virginia Hospital Association. The papers include annual reports, committee reports, policy proposals, as well as personal and professional correspondence from 1950-1953. The papers focus on issues like standardization of nursing education, hospital insurance consolidation and reform, hospital finances, and indigent patient care.
Arrangement
Collection arranged in original order.
Contents List
- Personal Papers 1950-1953
  This series contains personal and professional papers in original order. Each folder will include official committee reports as well as personal and professional correspondence. Most correspondence will be within the Executive Committee of the Virginia Hospital Association and will include Roy C. Brown, William J. Lees, and Homer E. Alberti.
  - Personal and Professional papers November 1950 - August 1951 (Folder 1.1)
  - Personal and Professional papers August 1951 - December 1951 (Folder 1.2)
  - Personal and Professional papers January 1952 - July 1952 (Folder 1.3)
  - Personal and Professional papers June 1952 - September 1952 (Folder 1.4)
  - Personal and Professional papers October 1952 - December 1952 (Folder 1.5)
  - Personal and Professional papers January 1953 - April 1953 (Folder 1.6)
  - Personal and Professional papers April 1953 - July 1953 (Folder 1.7)
- Medical College of Virginia Alumni Association papers 1955 - 1963
  This series contains correspondence related to Cardwell's work with the MCV Alumni Association. Cardwell served on the editorial board of the Scarab. Enclosed are several issues of the Scarab, an article from the Southern Medical Journal, as well as professional correspondence.
  - Alumni Records 1955 - 1963 (Folder 2.1)
    - The Scarab (Folder 2.1)
      Vol. 7 No.2
    - The Scarab (Folder 2.1)
      Vol. 8 No. 1
    - The Scarab (Folder 2.1)
      Vol. 9 No 4
    - The Scarab (Folder 2.1)
      Vol. 12 No 4
    - A Time for Tribute, Southern Medical Journal, Vol. 51 No.2 (Folder 2.1)